Anne McCaffrey Papers
Anne McCaffrey Papers
1947-1967
McCaffrey, Anne.
4.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, memorabilia, and writings.
149155
Biographical History
Anne McCaffrey (1926-2011) was an American-Irish author, best known for her Dragonriders of Pern books (Dragonflight, Dragonquest, Dragonsinger, etc.). Many of her novels feature strong female characters; McCaffrey has been widely quoted as saying that her novel Restoree, for example, was intended as a rebuttal to the way women were usually portrayed in science fiction.
She has won numerous awards and accolades, including becoming the first woman to win a Hugo Award (1968) and the first to win a Nebula Award (1969). In 1999, she received the American Library Association's Margaret A. Edwards Award for lifetime achievement in writing for teens. In 2005 she was named a Grand Master of the Science Fiction and Fantasy Writers of America (SFWA), and was inducted into the Science Fiction Hall of Fame in 2006. Since her death, her son Todd McCaffrey has continued writing books set in the Pern universe.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Anne McCaffrey Papers consist of correspondence, memorabilia and writings.
The small amount of Correspondence includes letters from author and editor John W. Campbell, as well as McCaffrey's agent Virginia Kidd. There are also a few other letters from publishers and editors. Miscellaneous correspondence includes a chatty personal letter from someone named Ida, evidently a close friend.
Memorabilia is also quite small. It includes a few photographs and a cover from Analog Science Fiction, with one of McCaffrey's stories featured.
Writings comprises the bulk of the collection. Here may be found drafts and working copy related to several of McCaffrey's books, including Decision at Doona, Dragonquest, Restoree, and The Ship Who Sang. Several of these have alternate early or working titles; for example, material filed under "And all the weyrs of Pern" and "Weyrleader" appears to consist largely of content that eventually became Dragonquest. Also in this series are extensive early drafts and working copy for a number of published and unpublished short stories, not all of which are science fiction, as well as a draft of McCaffrey's honors thesis on Russian science fiction author Yevgeny (Eugene) Zamiatin.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically by type and within that alphabetically by title.
Related Material
has an extensive collection of science fiction and fantasy novels, including many by Anne McCaffrey; please consult to locate these items.
See also the
Grove Press Records: Books: Book files: McCaffrey, Anne
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Women Authors; Science fiction; Literature -- American Fiction; Campbell, John W., Jr. (John Wood), 1910-1971.; Kidd, Virginia.; McCaffrey, Anne.; American literature -- 20th century.; Dragons -- Fiction.; Fantasy fiction, American.; Science fiction -- Women authors.; Science fiction, American.; Space ships -- Fiction.; Telepathy -- Fiction.; Women authors, American.; Women novelists, American.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Anne McCaffrey, 1968, 1970
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Campbell, John W., 1967; 1969; editor of Analog (Box 1)
  - Kidd, Virginia, 1966-1967; includes her comments/feedback on several of McCaffrey's novels (Box 1)
  - L.W. Singer Co. (Win Catherwood), 1967; regarding proposed juvenile title Dragonboy (Box 1)
  - Science Fiction Plus (Sam Moskowitz), 1953; acceptance letter for McCaffrey's first published story; magazine's bio of her (Box 1)
  - Walker & Company (Toby Roxborough), includes description of "situation at the onset of Dragonquest" (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, rejection letters from Galaxy, F&SF, Astounding; personal chatty letters with first names only (Judy, Ida) (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Analog Science Fiction cover, Feb 1969; McCaffrey's name on front as featured author for "A Womanly Talent" (Box 1)
  - "Moonwalker," Space-General Corporation, about adapting a lunar rover as assistive device for amputee children; product information and photos of young boy using it (Box 1)
  - Photographs, house labelled on back as "1509 Crossett Drive"; young boy who resembles the one in the Moonwalker photos; unidentified man circa 1940s (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, SFWA membership application for Florence Engel Randall; random notes (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Books
    - And all the weyrs of Pern, unrelated to the 1991 book with similar title; appears to largely be very early drafts of material eventually published as Dragonquest (1971)
      - Working copy, heavy edits, multiple drafts, inconsistent pagination, insertions, etc.; 5 folders (Box 1)
      - Draft, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Decision at Doona
      - Working copy, 1967; heavy edits, multiple drafts, inconsistent pagination, insertions, etc.; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Draft A, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Draft B, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Draft C, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Draft D, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous pages (Box 2)
    - Dragonflight
      - Working copy, with heavy edits, multiple drafts, inconsistent pagination, insertions, etc.; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Draft A, photocopy of edited typescript, 342 pp.; 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Draft B, photocopy of edited typescript, 342 pp.; may be identical to Draft A; 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Dragonquest
      - Synopsis (Box 3)
      - Working copy, with heavy edits, multiple drafts, inconsistent pagination, insertions, etc. (Box 3)
      - Working copy cont., with heavy edits, multiple drafts, inconsistent pagination, insertions, etc.; 7 folders (Box 4)
      - Draft, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - The partnered ship, noted on folder as "unpublished segment of The Ship Who Sang"
      - Working copy, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Draft, typescript carbon, 70 pp. (Box 4)
    - Postscript at Pull In Point
      - Draft, typescript carbon, 236 pp.; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Draft fragments, some have alternate title, Panic at Pull In Point (Box 5)
    - Restoree
      - Draft A, typescript carbon with corrections, 235 pp.; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Draft B, typescript carbon with corrections, 324 pp.; 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Draft C, typescript carbon with corrections, 324 pp.; 5 folders (Box 5)
      - Draft C, printer's copy, photocopy, with some notes and additional corrections; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Galleys, corrected, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous pages (Box 6)
    - Thie ship who sang, a novelization of five short stories, previously published between 1961 and 1969
      - Parts 1-4, drafts, 6 folders (Box 6)
      - Bridging section and part 5, draft (Box 7)
      - Printer's copy, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous drafts, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Straight on til morning
      - Draft, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Turn turtle
      - Draft A, incomplete, 85 pp. (Box 7)
      - Draft B, typescript with corrections, 218 pp.; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Research material, notes, etc. (Box 8)
    - Weyrleader, appears to be material eventually published as Dragonquest
      - Working copy, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Plays
    - The faculty meeting (Box 8)
    - Fiftieth anniversary celebration of the Presbyterian Church of Upper Montclair, 1957; incomplete drafts, typescripts (Box 8)
    - The unknown Ajax, two drafts; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Fragments (Box 8)
  - Poetry
    - Fragments (Box 8)
  - Short stories
    - Atlas' pebble (Box 8)
    - Bitter talent (alt title: Talent bearer), 2 drafts (Box 8)
    - The chicken's egg (Box 8)
    - Dramatic mission, 2 drafts (Box 8)
      See also Books: The Ship who Sang, of which this forms part 4.
    - The fare on the Styx, draft and a few miscellaneous pages (Box 8)
    - Get off the unicorn, multiple drafts, handwritten and typed (Box 8)
    - The great canine chorus, numerous drafts and draft fragments; earlier drafts are titled "Goose girl"; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - The greatest love / Charley's aunt, draft (Box 9)
    - Horse from a different sea, drafts (Box 9)
    - Is not tomorrow, draft (Box 9)
    - A job for charity, 2 drafts (Box 9)
    - The Lady in the tower, noted on folder as "pub April '59 F & SF"; other titles: Callisto Commutation and Last Carnaval [sic] (Box 9)
    - Lilacs, page 1 missing (Box 9)
    - Nick Knack (Box 9)
    - Opening night at Aurigae (Box 9)
    - She tried hard, incomplete, ends on p. 7 (Box 9)
    - The ship who sang, photocopy of publication in Magazine of Fantasy and Science Fiction, with note from Ballantine Books referring to it as "setting copy"; possibly as used in the full-length novel (Box 9)
    - The sound of breathing (Box 9)
    - A womanly talent, working copy and draft; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - [Untitled], re: angel living in back yard (Box 9)
    - [Untitled], re: Professor Darby, equations (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous
    - "Dragonboy", outline for story about F'lar's childhood (Box 9)
    - "Eugene Ivanovich Zamiatin, with special emphasis on his Utopian novel, We", 1947; honor's thesis at Radcliffe (Box 9)
    - Notes for unidentified speech, incomplete, but relates to science fiction writing (Box 9)
    - Pern notes, lists, hand-drawn map, etc. (Box 9)
    - [Thomas the cat] (Box 9)
    - "Worlds redeemed", working copy for novel or short story (Box 9)
    - Fragments, unidentified (Box 9)